{"tossups": [{"question": "In the aftermath of this event, the British government allowed the Kindertransport program to be set up by the Refugee Children\u2019s Movement. A speech noting that demonstrations \u201cshould not be prepared or organized\u201d but \u201care not to be hampered\u201d helped fuel this event, which was triggered after Herschel Grynszpan assassinated diplomat Ernst vom Rath. SA Brownshirts carried out, for ten points, what massive attack on the night of November 9, 1938 against Jewish stores and synagogues in Germany?", "answer": "<b> Kristallnacht</b> (or the<b> Night of Broken Glass</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "An 1869 Supreme Court case involving this state held that its bond sales during the Civil War were invalid. The Gun Free School Zones Act was ruled unconstitutional in a case arising from this state,<em> US</em> <em>v. Lopez</em>. The Supreme Court overturned<em> Bowers v. Hardwick</em> in a 2003 case that struck down this state\u2019s anti-sodomy laws. Abigail Fisher challenged the affirmative action program of, for ten points, what state that admits the top ten percent of each of its high school\u2019s students to its main campus in Austin?", "answer": "<b> Texas</b> (accept<b> Texas</b> v. White; accept Lawrence v.<b> Texas</b> after \u201cBowers\u201d is read; accept Fisher v. University of<b> Texas</b> after \u201cAbigail\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this country, independence leader and human rights activist Hannah Kudjoe created an anti-nudity campaign and distributed clothes. Operation Cold Chop deposed a ruler of this country who was part of the Big Six and founded the Convention People\u2019s Party. The \u201cMotion of Destiny\u201d speech called for the independence of this nation, where the Akosombo dam was built on the Volta River by Kwame Nkrumah. The British colony of Gold Coast controlled what is now, for ten points, what West African country governed from Accra?", "answer": "<b> Ghana</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this war, a group of soldiers under Thomas Wheeler were ambushed and besieged at Brookfield. This war erupted after a group of men were hung for their supposed role in the murder of John Sassamon. The Great Swamp Fight occurred in this war, during which one side was led by the chieftain Metacomet. The Wampanoag fought against colonists in New England in, for ten points, what 17th century war named after a royal moniker?", "answer": "<b> King Philip</b>\u2019s War (accept<b> First Indian</b> War; accept<b> Metacom</b>et\u2019s War before \u201cMetacomet\u201dis read; accept rebellion and other equivalent terms for war)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler forced Catus Decianus to flee to Gaul after a decisive victory at Great Wratting. This ruler defeated Quintus Cerialis at Camulodunum after launching a campaign in response to Roman refusal to honor the will of Prasutagus, but the eventual arrival of Suetonius led to this ruler\u2019s defeat at Watling Street near Londinium. The Nero-era revolt of the Iceni was led by, for ten points, what queen who fought the Romans over control of Britain in AD 60?", "answer": "<b> Boudica</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This politician dueled fellow state representative Humphrey Marshall after a spat regarding British cloth. As Speaker, this man succeeded in convincing Southern representatives to adopt the Thomas Proviso, while also convincing Northern representatives to allow Missouri\u2019s admission into the Union as a slave state. This coiner of the term \u201cAmerican System\u201d negotiated a \u201ccorrupt bargain\u201d that resulted in John Quincy Adams\u2019 elevation to the presidency. For ten points, name this Kentucky politician known as the Great Compromiser.", "answer": "Henry<b> Clay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader was embroiled in scandal after his wife was linked to a super-nationalistic kindergarten. This man proposed a new holiday, Restoration of Sovereignty Day, first celebrated in 2013. This leader planned an increase in the consumption tax as part of the Three Arrows, his signature economic plan. This leader rules in partnership with the Komeito Party and succeeded Junichiro Koizumi in his current post. For ten points name this current prime minister of Japan.", "answer": "Shinzo<b> Abe</b> ([ah-bay], but be lenient)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This ruler launched a military intervention to support John Zapolya against his rival Ferdinand I. Though this ruler signed the Treaty of Amasya to end an inconclusive war with the Safavid Empire, he was more successful in forcing the Knights Hospitaller out of Rhodes to gain control of the Mediterranean. This ruler was victorious at the Battle of Mohacs [moh-hotch] over Louis II of Hungary while expanding into Europe. For ten points, name this longest reigning Ottoman sultan, known as \u201cthe Magnificent.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Suleiman</b> the Magnificent (or<b> Suleiman</b> I)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man ordered the death penalty to be carried out on a man who had destroyed his own frontal lobe, Ricky Ray Rector. One of this man\u2019s failed investments led to Jim and Susan McDougal being investigated by independent counsel Kenneth Starr. Proceedings in a lawsuit filed by Paula Jones against this man were cited in charges of perjury and obstruction of justice brought before the Senate in 1999. For ten points, name this politician whose sexual misconduct led to the second Presidential impeachment trial in history.", "answer": "William Jefferson \u201cBill\u201d<b> Clinton</b> (accept William Jefferson<b> Blythe</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A speech given by this man claims that, though Cassius Clay could also sing, it was swinging that made him a world champion. In 2010, Thomas Hagan was formally paroled for his murder of this man, who gave the \u201cBallot or the Bullet\u201d speech in 1964. This man took the name name Detroit Red as a criminal; while imprisoned for robbery, he adopted the teachings of Elijah Muhammad. For ten points, name this civil rights activist and member of Nation of Islam who replaced his given surname Little with a single letter.", "answer": "<b> Malcolm X</b> (accept Malcolm<b> Little</b> before mentioned; accept el-Hajj<b> Malik el-Shabazz</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One of these events ended after Mike Jones was barely able to stop Kevin Dyson. In the aftermath of one of these events, Trent Dilfer was non-traditionally picked for an ad</b> <b>campaign instead of a man arrested for murder the prior year, (+)</b> <b>Ray Lewis. Malcolm</b> <b>Butler secured a victory in one of these events by intercepting (*)</b> Russell Wilson, and in 2017, a 28 to 3 lead was blown, causing Atlanta\u2019s second loss in this event. The Vince Lombardi Trophy is awarded to the winners of, for ten points, what championship game of the National Football League?", "answer": "<b> Super Bowl</b>s (prompt on (playoff) football game; prompt on (NFL) championship game)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Oster Conspiracy was planned in case this meeting failed to prevent the launch of Operation Green. A letter denouncing this meeting noted that the country was \u201coffered a choice between war and shame. She has chosen shame and will get war.\u201d (+) Edvard Benes resigned over this meeting, which resulted in the First Vienna Award. This meeting was proclaimed to have secured (*)</b> \u201cpeace for our time\u201d by Neville Chamberlain. For ten points, name this 1938 meeting in which the Allies appeased Germany by allowing Hitler to annex the Sudetenland.", "answer": "<b> Munich</b> Conference", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Enemy forces were removed from one of these regions in Operation Hastings, which used the Rockpile as an observation post; that one of these regions was north of the Khe Sanh Combat Base in Vietnam. When Arthur Bonifas and Mark Barrett were killed in another of these regions, US forces responded with Operation (+) Paul Bunyan, the heavily supported cutting of a poplar tree that was supposedly planted by Kim Il-Sung. (*)</b> Panmunjom and a Joint Security Area are located in one of these areas along the 38th Parallel between North and South Korea. For ten points, give this term for buffer territory between hostile countries where military personnel are banned.", "answer": "<b> Demilitarized Zone</b> (accept<b> DMZ</b>; accept Vietnamese<b> Demilitarized Zone</b>; accept Korean <b>Demilitarized Zone</b> after \u201cArthur Bonifas\u201d is read) (6) <b>This man asserted he was the rightful ruler of his country in a letter to Pope John</b> <b>XXII [22], the Declaration of Arbroath. The Earl of Pembroke was ordered to hunt down</b> <b>this man, handing him a disastrous loss at Methven. This king was (+)</b> <b>excommunicated</b> <b>after murdering John Comyn at the church of the Greyfriars. This man besieged (*)</b> Stirling Castle, forcing the Battle of Bannockburn. For ten points, name this victorious king of the First War of Scottish Independence. ANSWER:<b> Robert I</b> (accept<b> Robert</b> the<b> Bruce</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This ruler\u2019s mother placed a nail in his helmet, believing it to be a nail from the crucifixion. This ruler and his mother, Helena, are revered as \u201cEqual to the Apostles\u201d</b> <b>in the Eastern (+)</b> <b>Orthodox Church. This ruler, who had his son Crispus and his</b> <b>wife Fausta executed in 326, believed he received a divine (*)</b> sign before his victory at the Battle of Milvian Bridge. The Council of Nicaea was convened by, for ten points, what Roman emperor who promoted religious toleration with the Edict of Milan and converted the empire to Christianity?", "answer": "<b> Constantine the Great</b> (or<b> Constantine I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}